Inventory of the Robert West Beyers papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Robert West Beyers papers
1962-1969
2014C42
Beyers, Robert West, 1931-2002.
5 manuscript boxes (2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Speeches and writings, correspondence, notes, press releases, memoranda, and printed matter, relating to work of the Council of Federated Organizations (composed of the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee and other organizations) in carrying out a voter registration drive among black citizens of Mississippi in 1964, involvement of Northern college student volunteers, and attendant violence.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives. Material in the papers was previously a part of the New Left Collection, Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Searchworks at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Searchworks is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
New Left collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical/Historical Note
1931 Born, New York City
1953 B.A., Cornell University
1954-1955 Public relations director, U.S. National Student Association
1956-1961 Assistant managing editor, University of Michigan News Service
1961-1990 Director, Stanford University News Service
1964 Volunteer communications coordinator, Mississippi Summer Project
1990-1995 Volunteer associate editor, Pacific News Service
2002 Died, Palo Alto, California
Scope and Content of Collection
While Robert W. Beyers had a long and varied journalistic career as director of the Stanford University News Service and in other capacities, his papers in the Hoover Institution Archives are narrowly focused on a single episode in that career, the Mississippi Summer Project of 1964. The project was sponsored by a number of civil rights organizations, the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee foremost among them, grouped together as the Council of Federated Organizations. Its goal was to secure voter registration of black Mississippians and otherwise to promote improvement of their condition in what was widely considered to be the most thoroughly segregated state in the country.
The project depended heavily on college student volunteers from the North to carry out this work. Approximately forty Stanford University student volunteers participated in the project. Beyers, taking leave from his job, joined them as volunteer communications coordinator for four weeks in June and July 1964. The project predictably elicited strong opposition from the Mississippi power structure, including local law enforcement officers. Incidents of harassment, arrest, intimidation and violence culminated in the murder of three civil rights workers. Although concrete immediate achievements of the Mississippi Summer Project were limited, it did draw national attention to the condition of blacks in the Deep South and to the broader national civil rights movement.
The collection includes correspondence, internal memoranda, circulated materials and press clippings, documenting the project from a number of perspectives. These include the Stanford University community; the Council of Federated Organizations on the scene in Mississippi; the white Mississippian response, as seen from local newspaper coverage; and the national public reaction, as reflected in national press coverage.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Civil rights--United States.; African Americans--Civil rights.; Council of Federated Organizations (U.S.); Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (U.S.)
Collection Contents
- Personal File, 1963-1966. (Box 1)
  Correspondence, writings, notes and personal documents generated by Robert W. Beyers relating to the Mississippi Summer Project
  - Mississippi Summer Project data sheet, 1964 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - 1964 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - 1965 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - Undated (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Speech material, 1964-1965. (Box-folder 1: 5)
    Drafts and notes for talks at Stanford University and in the San Francisco Bay Area about Mississippi Summer Project
  - Press releases, 1963-1965. (Box-folder 1: 6)
    Drafts and final press releases for Council of Federated Organizations in Mississippi and for Stanford University News Service
  - Incident reports, 1964 (Box-folder 1: 7)
    Draft and final reports of incidents of violence and discrimination associated with the Mississippi Summer Project. Includes interview summaries by Beyers and affidavits
  - Mississippi notes, 1964-1966 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Miscellaneous notes, undated (Box-folder 1: 9)
- Stanford University File, 1963-1969. (Box 2)
  Circulated materials, newsletters and radio broadcast transcripts relating to Stanford University student participation in the Mississippi Summer Project
  - General, 1964-1969. (Box-folder 2: 1)
    Circulars, lists and newsletters emanating from the Stanford University and Bay Area community about the Mississippi Summer Project. Includes lists of participating Stanford students and newsletters of Bay Area support groups
  - Luke Kabat writings, 1964 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    Circulated typescript and mimeographed letters by Kabat, a Stanford student volunteer in Mississippi
  - KZSU (Stanford University), 1963-1965. (Box-folder 2: 3)
    Radio broadcast transcripts and reports about coverage of civil rights activities in the South
- Council of Federated Organizations File, 1963-1965. (Box 2-3)
  Circulars, reports, memoranda and other issuances by the Council of Federated Organizations relating to the Mississippi Summer Project
  - Prospectus, leaflets and announcement of Mississippi Summer Project, 1964 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Background studies, 1963-1964. (Box-folder 2: 5)
    Includes "Outline for Projected Black Belt Program," "The General Condition of the Mississippi Negro," "The Mississippi Legislature" and "On Arkansas in General"
  - Circulars, internal memoranda and reports relating to progress of the Mississippi Summer Project, 1964-1965 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Incident reports of violence and discrimination associated with the Mississippi Summer Project, 1964-1965 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Freedom Schools reports and circulars, 1964 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    Includes Southern Teaching Program report
  - Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party. Press releases, circulars and resolutions, 1964-1965. (Box-folder 3: 2)
    Includes report, "Mississippi: How Negro Democrats Fared"
- Printed Matter, 1962-1966. (Box 3-5)
  Flyers, leaflets, pamphlets, printed articles, clippings and other printed matter relating to the Mississippi Summer Project and civil rights in the South
  - Congress of Racial Equality issuances, 1962-1965 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People issuances, 1964-1966 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - National Committee to Abolish the House Un-American Activities Committee issuances, 1963-1965 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference issuances, 1964-1966 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - Southern Conference Educational Fund issuances, 1964 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee issuances, 1964-1966 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Miscellaneous civil rights organization issuances, 1964-1966 (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - United States government issuances (mainly by the Department of Justice), 1963-1965 (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - Mississippi Black Paper (documentary publication), 1965 (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - Sequoia (Stanford University literary magazine). Special issue focusing on the Mississippi Summer Project, 1965 (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - Tucker, Shirley, Mississippi from Within, 1965 (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - Printed miscellany, 1964-1966. (Box-folder 3: 14)
    Includes anti-communist circulars, special issue of Jet on Mississippi, and journal article reprints
    - National press coverage of the Mississippi Summer Project and civil rights in the South (Box 3-4)
    - 1962-1963 (Box-folder 3: 15)
    - 1964 January-June (Box-folder 3: 16)
    - 1964 July-August (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - 1964 September-December (Box-folder 4: 2)
    - 1965 (Box-folder 4: 3)
    - 1966 (Box-folder 4: 4)
    - Undated (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Stanford and Bay Area press coverage of the Mississippi Summer Project and civil rights in the South (Box 4)
    - 1963 (Box-folder 4: 6)
    - 1964 (Box-folder 4: 7)
    - 1965-1966 and undated (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Mississippi press coverage of the Mississippi Summer Project and civil rights in the South (Box 5)
    - 1963 (Box-folder 5: 2)
    - 1964 March-June (Box-folder 5: 3)
    - 1964 July (Box-folder 5: 4-5)
    - 1964 August-November (Box-folder 5: 6)
    - 1965-1966 (Box-folder 5: 7)